Guide to the Records of the Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis Conference RISM RG 16(h)
New York University Archives
RISM Conference Papers: Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis
1973-1975
RISM RG 16(h)
New York University Archives
5.4 linear feet
The August 1973 Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis Conference convened in Chicago, Illinois. The Conference was part of the Ninth International Congress of the International Union of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences. The RISM Conference Papers: Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis documents the planning of the 1973 Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis Conference and the process between 1973 and 1975 to publish a volume of papers that were presented by its attendees.
Ninth International Congress of the International Union of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences.
Scope and Content
The RISM Conference Papers: Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis documents the planning of the 1973 Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis Conference and the process between 1973 and 1975 to publish a volume of papers that were presented by its attendees. The bulk of the collection is composed of subject files that contain correspondence, drafts of research papers, and other documents concerning an individual contributor to the conference and/or volume. There are also a number of folders containing information related to the administrative aspects of both the conference and publication, including budgets, proposals, grants, correspondence with publishers, and drafts of the volume’s front matter. Other highlights found in the collection are a cache of biographies and resumes of featured scientists, materials relating to other conferences on Cannabis, and invitations and programs from the 1973 Conference.
Arrangement Note
The RISM Conference Papers: Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis are arranged into a single series: Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis.
Historical Note
The August 1973 Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis Conference convened in Chicago, Illinois. The Conference was part of the Ninth International Congress of the International Union of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences. The goal of the Conference was to assemble and review the work going on in different fields of cannabis research. Interest and public concern stemming from the 1960s “drug culture” and rising awareness of drug use resulted in both the private and government funding of multi-disciplinary cannabis research. The conference was attended by anthropologists, botanists, geneticists, pharmacists, psychiatrists, and sociologists. Topics covered included: the origins of cannabis use, its social and cultural impact, expansion of the plant's commercial and medical use, surveys of contemporary marijuana use across the globe, and comparative studies of traditional cannabis use by religious and geographic groups throughout history. The papers presented at the conference were collected and published in a volume entitled Cannabis and Culture. Vera Rubin of the Research Institute for the Study of Man oversaw the production and wrote the introduction.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Additionally, please note that this collection is stored
offsite
, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Benet, Sula, 1903-1982; Du Toit, Brian M., 1935-; Green, Melvyn; Hasan, K. A., (Khwaja A.); International Union of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences.; Khalifa, Ahmed; Li, Hui-Lin, 1911-; Miller, Ralph D.; Munir Khan, 1911-; Partridge, William L.; Rubin, Vera D.; Schaeffer, Joseph H.; Schultes, Richard Evans; Van der Merwe, Nicholaas; Administrative records.; Anthropology.; Articles.; Authors and publishers |z United States.; Biographies.; Correspondence.; Drug abuse |x Study and teaching.; Manuscripts (document genre).; Marijuana.; Medicinal plants.; Proceedings.; Research (document genres).
- Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Cannabis
  - Administrative: SI, NIMH (correspondence) Carroll, Douglas Ashenfelter, Stanley., 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pre- and Post-Conference Expenditures Vouchers, etc., 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Proposal, Contract, Accounting, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Table of Contents Introduction-Acknowledgements, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Resumes: Cannabis and Culture, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographies and Participant Observers, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beaubrun, Michael H., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Benet, Sula, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Benoist, Jean, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Blaine, Jack D. and Bozzetti, Louis, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bozzettie, Louis and Blaine, Jack, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Burchard, Roderick E., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Carroll, Eleanor, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Li, Hui-Lin, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Carter, William E., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Codere, Helen (Draft paper, photograph), 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Comitas, Lambros, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - de Pinho, Alvaro Rubim, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rios de, Marlene D., 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - du Toit, Brian M., 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - du Toit, Brian M., 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Elejalde, Rafael, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fisher, James, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hasan, Khwaja A. Paper, Summary and Abstract, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hasan, K.A. (Khwaja A.), 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Hutchinson, H. W. (Harry William), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Royal Commission on Non-Medical Use of Drugs (Canada), 1954-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Joseph, Roger, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Kaplan, John, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Khalifa, Ahmad, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Khan, Munir A., 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Martin, Marie (plus photographs), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Post-Conference Correspondences re Publication of Volume, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Post-Conference Correspondence, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Pre-Conference Correspondence, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - IXth International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences Binder, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mouton Publishers: author's questionnaire and publication correspondence, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Aldine Publishing (Morin), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Mouton Publishing, 1975-1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Drafts sent to Sally Olds (V.R.), 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - McGlothlin, William H. (1 of 2), 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - McGlothlin William H. (2 of 2), 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miller, Ralph D. and Green, Mel, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miller, Ralph D. (Green, Mel), 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Congress: ICAES Chicago, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tentative Participant:Khan, Munir, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tentative Participant: Lee, Richard Borshay, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Tentative Participant:Labarre, Weston, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Tentative Participant: Barash, Lucille, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Tentative Participant: Barnett, Milton, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Tentative Participant: Jones, T. Reese, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Tentative Participant:Singer, Philip and Araneta, Erique, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Tentative Participant: Nahas, Gabriel G., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Tentative Participant:Watt, Prof. John M., 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Tentative Participants, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Cannabis Conference Invatations/Rejections, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Furst, Peter T., 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Williams-Garcia, Roberto (1 of 2), 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Williams-Garcia, Roberto (2 of 2), 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Observers, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Palgi, Phyllis (1 of 2), 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Palgi, Phyllis (2 of 2), 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Partridge, William (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Patridge, William (2 of 2), 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Films, slides, exhibits, and videotapes, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Final Drafts-Programs, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Myerhoff, Barbara (1 of 2), 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Myerhoff, Barbara (2 of 2), 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rubin, Vera (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Rubin, Vera (2 of 2), 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Cannabis Conference-V.R. I, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Cannabis Conference-V.R. II, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Stearn, William T., 1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Schultes, Richard Evans (1 of 2), 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Schultes, Richard Evans (2 of 2), 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Schaeffer, Joseph (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Schaeffer, Joseph (2 of 2), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Segelman, Alvin B. (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Segelman, Alvin B. (2 of 2), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Shokeid, Moshe, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Stablein, William, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Stefanis, Costas (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Stefanis, Costas (2 of 2), 1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Van der Merwe, Nikolaas J., 1976 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Wilber, Johannes, 1972-1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Conference on Therapeutic Aspects of Marijuana, 1975 November 6-7 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Transparencies, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Photographs and Diagrams, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Conference Articles, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Articles, 1972-1977 (Box 9, Folder 13)